Finding Aid for George Romney Papers 1920s-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Romney Papers 1920s-1973
Romney, George W., 1907-
852178 Aa 2
Republican Governor of Michigan, 1962-1969; Presidential candidate, 1968; Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, 1969-1972. Papers consist of extensive correspondence and subject files from his tenure as governor, campaign material, and files relating to service at HUD and his other political activities, includes photographs, films and videotapes and sound recordings.
600 linear feet
148 GB online
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of George Romney (donor no. 4703) and came to the library in 1969. Subsequent accessions were received in 1983 and 1985.
The collection is open for research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
All 2-inch videotapes and 16mm films in the Romney collection were digitized in 2009 and are available for use in the reading room on DVD. Streaming files were also created all streaming files are listed in this finding aid, but only a small selections are currently online. The latter can be viewed using the 'view video: link
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
George Romney was born on July 8, 1907 in Chihuahua, Mexico where his parents had gone to help establish a Mormon colony. Following missionary service in Scotland and England (1927-1928), Romney attended the University of Utah (1929) and George Washington University in Washington, D.C. (1929-1930). He served on the staff of U.S. Senator David I. Walsh in 1929-1930 as a tariff specialist, and afterward as an apprentice with the Aluminum Company of America and the Aluminum Wares Association. In 1931 he married Lenore LaFount.
From 1939 to 1948 Romney was employed by the Automobile Manufacturer's Association, serving as general manager from 1942 to 1948. In 1948 he joined the Nash-Kelvinator Corporation, and in 1954 became chairman and president of the newly formed American Motors Corporation.
In 1961, he was elected a Republican delegate to the Michigan Constitutional Convention, and served as its vice-president. In 1962, Romney decided to seek public office, announcing his candidacy for governor. He easily defeated Democratic incumbent John Swainson. A popular figure with the electorate, Romney was twice reelected. During the later part of his administration, he made a conscious bid for the Republican nomination for president. From about 1966 to 1968, George Romney, governor of Michigan, was an active candidate for the 1968 Republican nomination for president of the United States. Through most of 1967, Romney was in fact front-runner, but his candidacy rapidly faltered and Richard Nixon went on to become President.
Although there have been many reasons advanced for the failure of George Romney's campaign, at least part of the problem can be ascribed to the organizational machinery set up on his behalf, first, to assess his chances, and then, second, to seek delegate support. The fault, according to some national commentators, was the bifurcation of the campaign into two separate, and often, competing organizational arms: Romney Associates, headquartered in Lansing, Michigan, and Romney for President, headquartered in Washington, D.C.
Just when George Romney started thinking about the presidency is not clear. Perhaps the idea formed as a result of the national recognition he received from his leadership of American Motors in the 1950s. To this should be added his demonstrated voter appeal as evidenced by his overwhelming gubernatorial victories in 1962 and again in 1964. Party leaders were beginning to take Romney seriously. No wonder that sometime in 1965, Romney established a small office for himself in the Prudden Building in Lansing to answer the increasing correspondence he was receiving about national political issues, many of which urged him to run for president. After another resounding victory in 1966, Romney decided to have "a hard look" at his chances, and accordingly, he established Romney Associates, moving the files from the Prudden Building into an East Michigan Avenue office and shifting into leadership roles some of his most trusted political and administrative advisors, notably Robert J. McIntosh and Walter DeVries.
As established, Romney Associates was responsible for research, speech writing, press and public relations, scheduling and travel arrangements, and responding to the governor's out-of-state correspondence. At about the same time, believing that he needed a national presence, Romney selected Leonard Hall, former Republican National Chairman, to organize in Washington, D.C. a Romney-for-President Committee. The functions assigned to the Hall group included overall campaign strategy, searching out delegates, bringing together the various state Romney for President groups, preparing mailing lists, maintaining cordial relations with influential members of Congress, and planning for the nominating convention. Perhaps in the two organizations lay the seed of Romney's collapse as a candidate. Because of their geographic separateness and the frequent overlapping of functions, the Romney campaign was marked by internal conflicts and inefficiency. The candidate himself received much of the criticism and his stand on various issues was not as clear-cut as should be expected. Added to this was the resurgence of Richard Nixon as a viable candidate. Unfairly, some might argue, Romney's campaign was dead soon after his official announcement in November 1967; and that following the New Hampshire primary, in February 1968, Romney merely went through the motions, hoping for a political miracle that was not to be.
Following the election of Richard Nixon, Romney resigned as governor and went into the new president's cabinet as Secretary of Housing and Urban Development. He resigned in 1972 to retire to private life. In his later years, Romney was active in the promotion of citizen involvement in government affairs. George Romney died in 1995.
Summary Contents List
GOVERNOR'S PAPERS Subgroup
CHRONOLOGICAL (boxes 1-219)
1963
Boards and Commissions (boxes 1-27)
General Subjects (boxes 27-43)
Federal (boxes 44-46)
Military Affairs (boxes 46-47)
1964
Boards and Commissions (boxes 48-74)
General Subjects (boxes 75-86)
Federal (boxes 86-88)
Military Affairs (boxes 88-89)
1965
Boards and Commissions (boxes 89-114)
General Subjects (boxes 114-126; 419)
Legislative Files (boxes 127-128)
Federal (boxes 129-130)
Military Affairs (boxes 130-131)
1966
Boards and Commissions (boxes 131-154)
General Subjects (boxes 154-164)
Federal (boxes 165-166)
Legislative Files (boxes 166-167)
1967
Boards and Commissions (boxes 168-185)
General Subjects (boxes 186-194 and 343-346)
Federal (boxes 194-195)
Legislative Files (box 196)
1968
Board and Commissions (boxes 197-211)
General Subjects (boxes 212-217; 417-418)
Federal (boxes 217-218)
Legislative Files (box 219)
GOVERNOR'S OFFICE (boxes 220-352)
Topical file, 1962-1968: Margaret Little (boxes 220-227)
Press Office (boxes 228-292; 364; 427-438)
Topical files, 1963-1968 (boxes 228-246)
George T. Trumbull, Jr. files, 1965-1968 (box 247)
Speeches (boxes 248-266)
Speech material (boxes 267-270)
Biographical material/Romney Weekly Reports (box 271)
Special messages (box 272)
Proclamations (boxes 273-283)
Press releases (boxes 283-290)
Schedules (boxes 291-292)
Clippings (boxes 364 and 427-438)
Invitation Accepts (boxes 293-301)
Invitations (Lenore Romney) (boxes 302-303)
Governor Personal (boxes 304-313)
Staff Files (boxes 314-342 and 420-423)
Allen, Glenn (box 339)
Blizzard, Theodore (boxes 325-327)
Burns, J. Dennis (box 339)
Danhof, Robert. See Legal.
DeJong, Herbert (boxes 332-333)
DeVries, Walter (box 331)
Harmon, Charles (boxes 331 and 420)
Helmbrecht, Richard K. (boxes 420-421)
Human Resources Council (boxes 422-423)
Kapplinger, Lucille (box 421)
Kellogg, James C. (boxes 421-422)
Legal: Robert Danhof (boxes 314-324; 339; 420)
Detroit Riot (box 319)
Orlebeke, Charles (boxes 327-330 and 421-422)
Whitbeck, William (box 332)
Area Interests (boxes 334-338)
Civil Defense (box 334)
Governmental Reorganization (box 423)
Water (boxes 336-338)
Program Development (boxes 340-342)
Study Commissions/Governor's Conferences (boxes 347-352)
POLITICAL/MISCELLANEOUS (boxes 353-414 and 424-426)
Political Files (boxes 353-363 and 429)
Boards and Commissions appointments (boxes 379-396)
Extraditions (boxes 397-398)
Orders for Appointments (box 399)
State Board of Education Agenda (boxes 400-407)
Michigan Employment Security Commission (boxes 407-408)
Printed Material (boxes 408-413)
Miscellaneous (box 414 and 424-426)
State Capitol Building Restoration (box 424)
PRE-GUBERNATORIAL Subgroup
Biographical Information (box 1-E)
Correspondence, 1939-1962 (boxes 1-E--3-E)
Speeches/Articles, 1941-1962 (boxes 4-E--12-E)
Business Career (box 13-E)
Public Services (box 14-E--15-E)
Miscellaneous (box 15-E)
POST-GUBERNATORIAL Subgroup
HUD Subject Files (boxes 1-P--14-P)
Voluntary Action (boxes 14-P--16-P)
Concerned Citizens Movement (boxes 17-P--19-P)
Other Public Activities (boxes 19-P and 42-P)
Personal Papers, 1969-1973 (boxes 20-P--23-P)
Speeches, 1969-1973 (boxes 24-P--41-P)
VISUAL MATERIALS Subgroup
Photographs
Portraits/Pre-gubernatorial (box 1-V)
Gubernatorial, 1962-1968 (boxes 1-V--3-V and 14-V)
Post-gubernatorial (box 3-V)
Videotapes, 1962-1968 (digitized copies available for use)
Films, 1956, 1962-1967, and 1970 (digitized copies available for use)
Filmstrip (box 9-V)
SOUND RECORDINGS Subgroup
7 in. reel-to-reel sound tapes
1952-March 1962 (boxes 16-E--21-E)
March 1962-1969 (boxes 365-375)
5 in. reel-to-reel sound tapes
1955-September 1961 (box 21-E)
May 1962-1968 (boxes 376 and 415)
3 in. reel-to-reel sound tapes
April 1965-December 1966 (box 415)
Cassette tapes
September 1967-January 1969 (box 415)
Non-Romney tapes
Undated and 1960-1968 (boxes 415)
ROMNEY ASSOCIATES Subgroup
State Files, 1964-1968 (boxes 1-RA--44-RA)
Correspondence, 1967-1968 (boxes 44-RA--45 RA)
Administrative Files, ca. 1964-1968 (boxes 46-RA--61-RA)
Topical Files (boxes 61-RA--68-RA)
Clippings (boxes 69-RA--71-RA)
Miscellaneous and campaign paraphernalia (box 72-A)
The papers of George Romney document the many faceted career of an automobile executive, governor of Michigan, candidate for President, cabinet officer, and activist on behalf of volunteerism. In this electronic version of the finding aid to the Romney papers, there are six subgroups of materials. These are Gubernatorial Papers covering the period of 1962 to 1969, Pre-gubernatorial Papers covering the period before taking office in 1963, Post-gubernatorial Papers covering the period after 1968, records of Romney Associates (a group established during his bid for the presidency), Visual Materials covering mainly the period up to 1969, and Sound Recordings also covering up to 1969. There is some overlapping of dates, particularly around the time when Romney was first elected governor in 1962 and the period when he joined the Nixon administration in 1969. The researcher should also note that the papers of Lenore Romney are not part of this finding aid.
Subjects:
Michigan. Governor (1963-1969: Romney); Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Michigan. National Guard.; United States. Dept. of Housing and Urban Development.; American Motors Corporation.; Citizens for Michigan.; Concerned Citizens Movement.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); National Center for Voluntary Action.; Republican Party (Mich.); Republican Party (Mich.); Republican Party (Mich.); Republican Party (Mich.); Romney Associates.; Afro-Americans--Michigan.; Apportionment (Election law)--Michigan.; Automobile industry and trade.; Civil rights--United States.; Civil service--Michigan.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Education--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--1962.; Elections--Michigan--1964.; Elections--Michigan--1966.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Governors--Michigan.; Housing policy--United States.; Labor--Michigan.; Mormons--Michigan.; Natural resources--Michigan.; Presidents--United States--Election--1960.; Presidents--United States--Election--1968.; Presidents--United States--Election--1968.; Presidents--United States--Election--1968.; Republican Party (Mich.); Strikes and lockouts--Michigan.; Taxation--Michigan.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975.; Voluntarism.; Water.; Detroit (Mich.)--Riot, 1967.; Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore (Mich.); United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Adler, Morris.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Albion College.; American Motors Corporation.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Political parades and rallies.; Bay City (Mich.); Bentley, Alvin M. (Alvin Morell), 1918-1969.; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Camp Grayling (Mich.); Cavanagh, Jerome Patrick, 1928-1979.; Cobo, Albert E. (Albert Eugene), 1893-1957.; Detroit (Mich.)--Political parades and rallies.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Eastern Michigan University.; Employment.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Escanaba (Mich.); Fairs--Michigan.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Ford, Henry, 1917-1987.; Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-1998.; Griffin, Robert P. (Robert Paul), 1923-2015; Holland (Mich.); Howe, Gordie, 1928-; Hudson, Joseph L. (Joseph Lowthian), 1931-; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Hutchinson, J. Edward (Jesse Edward), 1914-1985; Sault Ste. Marie International Bridge (Sault Sainte Marie, Mich. and Sault Sainte Marie, Ont.); Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.; Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Maddy, Joseph E. (Joseph Edgar), 1891-1966.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan--Governor--Inauguration--1963.; Michigan--Governor--Inauguration--1965.; Michigan--Governor--Inauguration--1967.; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Muskegon (Mich.); Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Parades and processions.; Political elections--1962.; Political elections--1964.; Political elections--1966.; Political elections--1968.; Political elections--1970.; Politics and government--1961-1970.; Pontiac (Mich.); Reagan, Ronald.; Republican National Convention n (28th: 1964: San Francisco, Calif.); Republican National Convention n (29th: 1968: Miami Beach, Fla.); West Branch (Mich.); Governors--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Aerial photographs.; Filmstrips.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
American Motors Corporation.; Automobile industry and trade--United States--Management.; Elections--Michigan--1962.; Elections--Michigan--1964.; Elections--Michigan--1966.; Elections--Michigan--1968.; Elections--United States--1968.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Republican Party (Mich.); Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Sound recordings.; United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.; Governors--Michigan.
Contributors - Sound Recordings:
Cronkite, Walter.; Ferency, Zolton A., 1922-1993; Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-1998.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Reagan, Ronald.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Staebler, Neil, 1905-2000; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.
- Governor's Papers
  The gubernatorial collection of George Romney is the most important resource for the study of state government during the years 1963-1968. The collection presently totals 432 linear feet of correspondence, memoranda and official reports relating to all aspects of the workings of the executive branch of the state government. The great bulk of the files came to the library in 1969 when Romney left office; a few additional feet of materials came in 1983 as part of the William Milliken accession.
  The collection, overall, concerns the administration of the governor's office, the governor's relationship with the boards and commissions under his charge, and the governor's responsibility as the state's highest ranking executive officer in proposing legislation and in responding to public crises and constituent concerns. Specifically, the Romney papers provide a wide range of information on the governor's response to such continuing areas of concern as education, civil rights, housing, labor disputes, environmental protection, highway safety, public welfare, and taxation. During his terms in office, Romney also had to face such particular issues as the reapportionment of the state's congressional districts, the implementation of the 1963 state constitution, the National Guard's alleged misuse of state funds, the Detroit Riot of 1967, and the Detroit newspaper strike of 1967. Also affecting the content of the files is the fact that during these same years Romney was a serious presidential candidate; and as a result, the gubernatorial papers have extensive material relating to the study of state and national politics and Republican Party matters.
  In 1983, as part of a larger governor's papers project, the George Romney Collection was selected for reprocessing and reappraisal. The usability of the governor's papers as received precluded any thought of making extensive alteration in the file categories maintained by Romney's office. With slight modifications (primarily the combining of similar or overlapping series), the order of the files has been retained. The only rearrangement undertaken was in the ordering or grouping of series within the collection. Files maintained on a yearly basis were brought together as part of a Chronological series; files either covering a longer period of time or maintained by the governor's office as a unit have been grouped together as Governor's Office; and the remainder has been categorized as Political/Miscellaneous.
  As part of its own control system, the governor's office maintained a card index to Romney correspondents. This card file, located in boxes 440-448, provides name access to those individuals and organizations having dealings with the state's executive.
  - Chronological
    The Chronological Series consists of files maintained yearly by the governor's office. For each year from 1963 to 1968, the following categories of records were established: Boards and Commissions; General Subjects; Federal; Military Affairs; and Legislation.
    Boards and Commissions is a yearly set of records arranged alphabetically by the name of the state board or commission, also for elective executive offices (Attorney General, Secretary of State, the Auditor General, etc.). The following types of records may be included for the various boards and commissions: communications with the agency head, audits and other budgetary materials, minutes of meetings, reports, printed matter, and constituent mail. Much of this latter correspondence is of a routine character, and consists of citizen complaints or discussions of personal problems that normally come within the responsibility of a specific state department or commission.
    The organization of this set of records changed midway into Romney's years in office with the ratification of the new state constitution. Under the old constitution, Michigan had established a large number of fairly independent state boards and commissions. So for the years 1963-1965, the researcher should look directly within the alphabetical sequence for the name of the agency in which he/she is interested. After 1965, however, with the reorganization of the executive, the state made an effort to streamline its operations and to provide greater administrative control over the various agencies. Established were subject departments (conservation, education, commerce, etc.) which had responsibility over the formerly independent boards and commissions. The filing of the governor's papers reflected the change. Thus, Racing Commission, for example, once filed under R, is now filed under its parent body, the Department of Agriculture. The researcher should thus consult the Michigan Manual (1965-1966), pp. 211-261 for a listing of the various departments and commissions and their placement within the newly created state departments (Acts 380, Public Acts of 1965).
    General Subjects is a yearly set of files arranged alphabetically and consisting primarily of citizen correspondence on a wide variety of subjects. Although much of these files are of a routine character, the files do reflect the concerns of the people of the state to the issues of the day.
    Federal is a smaller sequence of records (primarily correspondence, reports and memoranda) documenting the governor's relationship with the Federal Government. The files have been maintained in their original order within the following categories: Miscellaneous (including communications on national topics such as the Peace Corps, the Vietnam War, etc.) U.S. Congress (House and Senate) Cabinet Departments (arranged alphabetically) Commissions and other regulatory agencies (arranged alphabetically) Legislation (federal legislation affecting Michigan)
    Military is a small set of records concerning the governor's relationship with the adjutant general and the National Guard, but also concerning veterans matters. Beginning in 1966 with the reorganization of the executive branch, these records came to be filed with Boards and Commissions under Military Affairs.
    Legislation is a small set of files consisting mainly of constituent correspondence on varying pieces of state legislation. There are no files for 1963 or 1964.
    - 1963
      - Boards and Commissions
        - Accident Fund Board (Box 1)
        - Accountancy Board (Box 1)
        - Administrative Board Meetings (folders for each bi-weekly meeting) (Box 1)
        - Administration, Department of
          - Budget, 1963/64 (Box 1)
          - Glen S. Allen, controller (Box 2)
          - Budget Policy Decisions (Box 2)
          - General (Box 2)
        - Aeronautics, Department of
          - James D. Ramsey, director (Box 2)
          - Budget, 1963/64 (Box 2)
          - General (Box 2)
          - Audit reports, annual reports, etc. (Box 2)
        - Aging Commission (Box 2)
        - Agriculture Department
          - Audit Report (Box 2)
          - G. McIntyre, director (minutes of meetings) (Box 2)
          - Budget, 1963/64 (Box 3)
          - Administrative Reports (Box 3)
          - General (Box 3)
          - Food and Standards Division (Box 3)
          - Botulism (smoked fish) (Box 3)
          - Botulism Control (Box 3)
          - Insecticides (Box 3)
          - Japanese Beetle (Box 3)
        - Alcoholism Board
          - Minutes (Box 3)
          - Budget, 1963/64 (Box 3)
        - Apple Commission (Box 3)
        - Architects, Professional Engineers and Land Surveyors, State Board of Registration for (Box 3)
        - Athletics Board of Control (Box 3)
        - Attorney General
          - Frank Kelley, Attorney General (Box 3)
          - General (Box 3)
          - Opinions (Box 4)
        - Auditor General
          - Billie Farnum, Auditor General (Box 4)
          - Administrative Reports (Box 4)
          - General (Box 4)
        - Banking Department
          - Budget, 1963/64 (Box 4)
          - General (Box 4)